A Guide to the Commissioners to Examine Claims in Norfolk records of the Auditor of Public Accounts, 1777-1836.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Commissioners to Examine Claims in Norfolk records of the Auditor of Public Accounts,
1777-1836.
The Library of Virginia
APA 235
Virginia. Auditor of Public Accounts.
.45 cu. ft. (1 box)
Administrative Information
Arranged alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
APA 235 was acquired prior to 1905.
Historical Information
In May 1777 the General Assembly appointed a commission to evaluate the losses of property that resulted from the burning of Norfolk in January 1776. The commission distinguished between property destroyed by the British and American troops and between property owners who were friendly or hostile to the American cause. The commission had the authority to summon witnesses and to take depositions. In October 1777 the General Assembly formed another commission to ascertain the damages to property burned by or used as barracks by American troops in Portsmouth, Suffolk, Great Bridge, and Norfolk County. In May 1778 the General Assembly appointed other commissioners to evaluate the damage to the burnt mills and houses in Norfolk County belonging to Robert Tucker. The records indicate that most of the property was destroyed by American troops. The schedule of valuation for the city of Norfolk lists the occupations of the claimants.
Scope and Content
xx
Commissioners to Examine Claims in Norfolk included Robert Andrews, Daniel Fisher, Richard Kello, and Joseph Prestis. Report and Journal of the Commissioners to Examine Claims in Norfolk, 1777, details procedures followed and also includes A Schedule of Claims Entered for Losses Sustained by the Late Inhabitants of the Borough of Norfolk, which details 216 claims. The schedule includes claim number, name and occupation of the claimant, number of houses, amount of real and personal property destroyed before 15 January 1775 and amount of real and personal property destroyed after 15 January 1775, how destroyed, proof of loss, and total amount of loss. The schedule distiguishes between losses caused by Lord Dunmore, troops of the state, and by order of the convention. The proof of loss includes names of deponents. Depositions (1-19) and (C-Q), substantiate the claims and include details of loss and often the occupation of the deponent. Rather than 19 depostions, there are actually 20, but two are numbered 10. Many of the depositions, C-Q, include wrappers only, so are not listed below. A Copy of the valuation of property destroyed in Norfolk by the orders of Col. Robert Howe when evacuated by VA and NC troops in 1776, undated, lists property owner, type of property and the value of the property. The valuation folder also includes depositions.
Depositions (1-19), 1777, offer detailed accounts of the activities in Norfolk between January 1-4, 1776, and provide evidence of destruction and plundering by State troops. The reverse of the deposition of William Ivey includes a list of George Abyvon's losses. Depositions (C-Q), 1777, provide evidence as to the loyalties of some of the inhabitants of the Norfolk. Many of these contain wrappers only.
Claim records, 1776-1786, consist of documentation related to various claims. These records consist mainly of affidavits and depositions, but also include other supplementary documentation such as acts, certificates, correspondence, court records, resolutions, valuations, and wills.
Distillery claims, XX-XX, include affidavits, certificates, and correspondence related to the destruction of the local distillery by Virginia troops. The distillery was managed by the firm of Jamieson, Campbell, Calvert and Co. Alexander Love was the managing partner of the distillery, which included many citizen partners.
Commissioners to Examine Claims in Portsmouth, Suffolk, Great Bridge and Norfolk County included William Cowper, John Driver, Niles King, Henry Riddick, Willis Riddick, and Worlick Westwood. These claims include both destruction of property by fire and damage sustained to houses used as barracks by soldiers. Report of the Commissioners to Examine Claims in Portsmouth, Suffolk, Great Bridge and Norfolk County, 1778, details procedures followed and includes several schedules: A Schedule of Valuation of the Houses Burnt and Destroyed at Portsmouth by the Troops of this State; Schedule Ascertaining the Damage Sustained by Sundry Houses in the town of Portmouth by Being Made Use of as Barracks by the Troops of the State; Schedule Ascertaining the Damage Sustained by Sundry Houses in the town of Suffolk by Being Made Use of as Barracks by the Troops of the State; Schedule of the Valuation of Sundry Homes in the town of Norfolk remaining Unvalued or Their Value Not Allowed by the Last Session of the Assembly; Schedule of the Valuation of the Housing Belonging to Robert Tucker on Wind Mill Point where the Fort is Erected; and Schedule Containing an Estimate of the Total Amount of the Different Valuations. These schedules list claimant name, property description, proof as to destruction (deponent), and valuation.
Contents List
- Commissioners to Examine Claims in Norfolk, 1777-1836.
  - Report and Journal of the Commissioners to Examine Claims in Norfolk, 1777-1778. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Depositions (1-19), 1777. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - James Nicholson (1)
    - John Rogers (2)
    - John Rogers (3)
    - Capt. Willis Williston (4)
    - William Chisholm (5)
    - John Chick (6)
    - Richard Jarvis (7)
    - Robert Smyth and John Bishop (8)
    - Capt. Arthur Smith (9)
    - James Maxwill (10)
    - William Ivey (10)
    - James Leitch (11)
    - William Goodchild (12)
    - Bartholomew Thompson (13)
    - Robert Britt (14)
    - Capt. John Smith (15)
    - William Ingram (16)
    - Mathew McVie (17)
    - Paul Watlington (18)
    - Sarah Smith (19)
  - Depositions (C-Q), 1777. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Thomas Newton, Jr. (D)
    - William Plum (F)
    - Paul Proby (H)
    - Daniel Hutchings (K)
    - William Ivey, William Smith and John Wilson (N)
    - Dr. James Taylor
  - Copy of the Valuation of the Property Destroyed in Norfolk by the Order of Col. Robert Howe When Evacuated by VA and NC Troops in 1776, undated. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Deposition - John Chick, Paul Wadlington, John Bell, Willis Wilson, John Mohun
    - Deposition - William Ivey
    - Deposition - John Woodside
    - Oath - Andrew Donald
- Commissioners to Examine the Claim of Robert Tucker (Town of Norfolk), 1778.
  - Deposition - Richard Taylor, 1778. (Box 1, Folder x)
  - Deposition - Philip Carberry, 1778. (Box 1, Folder x)
  - Deposition - Unidentified, List of Robert Tucker's property, 1778. (Box 1, Folder x)
  - Deposition - John Bowness, 1778. (Box 1, Folder x)
- Claims, 1778.
  - Claims (A-G), 1778. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Applewhite, Thomas - Affadavit, 1788.
    - Atkinson, James - Sentry pass, Deposition re: Samuel Willoughby, Will, 1776; 1777; 1782.
    - Bell, John - Deposition re: Thomas Newton, Sr., 1777.
    - Boush, Samuel - Affidavit, 1780.
    - Calvert, Joseph - Certificate of administration for the estate of Paul Loyall, 1791.
    - Conner, Charles - Assignee, William Wishart v. Cornelius Calvert (General Court), 1785.
    - Cooper, Charles - Deposition re: Samuel Wilson, 1777.
    - Gardner, John - Valuation of property, 1777.
    - Gilchrist, John - Affadavit, Guardian appointment for Thomas Gilchrist, 1788.
    - Graves, Mary - wrapper only, 1784.
  - Claims (H-K), xx-xx. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Harris, John - Affidavit, 1788.
    - Hutching, John - Affidavit, 1793.
    - Hutchings, Joseph, Col. - Act of the General Assembly, 1792.
    - Jamison, George, Sr. - Will (Currituck Co., NC); Affidavit; Power of Attorney, John Jamison and Molly Wilson to Ephraim Whitmore, 1784, 1792.
    - Kelsick, John - Affidavit; Resolution of the House of Delegates, 1778.
  - Claims (M-N), xx-xx. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Marnix, John - Certificate of administration; Affidavit, 1784, 1792.
    - Matear, William - Affidavit, 1783.
    - Matthews, Thomas - Affidavit, 1795.
    - Moseley, Alexander - Affidavit, 1784.
    - Newton, Thomas - Estimate of losses; Deposition of George Kelly, 1777.
- Commissioners to Examine Claims in Portsmouth, Suffolk, Great Bridge and Norfolk County, and Robert Tucker's Property, 1778.
  - Report of the Commissioners to Examine Claims in Portsmouth, Suffolk, Great Bridge and Norfolk County, and Robert Tucker's Property, 1778. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Depositions - Robert Tucker's Property, 1778. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Resolutions, 1836, undated.
  - Resolutions, undated. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Resolution of the House of Delegates, 1836. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Distillery, 1790-1791. (Box 1, Folder 12)